[The Heir]
[El Heredero]
[Episode 7]
[Episodio 7]
Eldest Young Master,
Joven Maestro mayor,
let's go.
vamos.
It's almost done.
Ya casi está listo.
We're running out of time, Eldest Young Master!
¡Se nos acaba el tiempo, joven amo mayor!
Right.
Bien.
Send all the servants in the house away
Despidan a todos los sirvientes de la casa.
so they won't be implicated.
para que no se vean implicados.
Go quickly.
Ve rápido.
Okay.
Bueno.
Where is your Eldest Young Master?
¿Dónde está vuestro joven amo mayor?
In his study.
En su estudio.
Luo Wensong,
Luo Wensong
I'm here for Ronghua.
Estoy aquí por Ronghua.
Since neither of you
Dado que ninguno de ustedes
has any feelings for the other,
tiene algún sentimiento por el otro,
why not let her off?
¿Por qué no la dejaron ir?
Just write the betrothal annulment letter.
Simplemente escribe la carta de anulación del compromiso matrimonial.
Luo Wensong,
Luo Wensong
did you hear me?
¿Me oíste?
Luo Wensong!
¡Luo Wensong!
Zhen,
Zhen,
look.
mirar.
Did I make it?
¿Lo logré?
Look.
Mirar.
They blended.
Se fusionaron.
I did it.
Lo hice.
This new inkstick...
Esta nueva barra de tinta...
I've finally made it.
¡Por fin lo he conseguido!
I made it!
¡Lo logré!
I finally made it!
¡Finalmente lo logré!
Eldest Young Master!
¡El joven amo mayor!
Quick...
Rápido...
Don't touch it!
¡No lo toques!
The day the inkstick is born
El día en que nació la barra de tinta
is also the day it is destroyed.
También es el día en que es destruido.
Eldest Young Master,
Joven Maestro mayor,
let's go!
¡vamos!
If we don't leave now, the officers will come!
¡Si no nos vamos ahora, vendrán los policías!
Officers?
¿Oficiales?
It's Heaven's will.
Es la voluntad del Cielo.
Luo Wensong,
Luo Wensong
what happened to your family?
¿Qué le pasó a tu familia?
Zhen.
Zhen.
Look.
Mirar.
Does what has befallen my family today
¿Qué le ha sucedido hoy a mi familia?
remind you of when the Li family lost
te recordará cuando la familia Li perdió
the Tribute Ink commission all those years ago?
¿El encargo de Tribute Ink de hace tantos años?
Why brought that up?
¿Por qué sacaste ese tema?
I was still young then.
Yo era todavía joven entonces.
I don't remember much.
No recuerdo mucho.
This inkstick
Esta barra de tinta
surpasses all others in the world.
supera a todos los demás en el mundo.
But
Pero
I refuse to hand it over to those vile,
Me niego a entregárselo a esos viles,
scheming scoundrels.
unos canallas intrigantes.
What should I do?
¿Qué tengo que hacer?
Ping'an.
Ping'an.
Burn them.
Quémalos.
Burn them?
¿Quemarlos?
Eldest Young Master!
¡El joven amo mayor!
You... You...
Tú... Tú...
What are you doing, Eldest Young Master?
¿Qué estás haciendo, joven amo mayor?
Well...
Bien...
What are you doing?
¿Qué estás haciendo?
You...
Tú...
Luo Wensong!
¡Luo Wensong!
You can't burn them!
¡No puedes quemarlos!
Don't burn them!
¡No los quemes!
Let go!
¡Déjalo ir!
Eldest Young Master!
¡El joven amo mayor!
Luo Wensong,
Luo Wensong
no matter what happened to your family,
No importa lo que le haya pasado a tu familia,
as long as you're alive
Mientras estés vivo
and still have your craft,
y aún así tener tu oficio,
there is always a chance to turn things around.
Siempre hay una oportunidad de cambiar las cosas.
But if you burn everything,
Pero si lo quemas todo,
there's no going back!
¡No hay vuelta atrás!
Everything will be gone!
¡Todo habrá desaparecido!
If it's gone, then so be it.
Si se ha ido, que así sea.
As the saying goes,
Como dice el dicho,
"When the Way prevails, one serves;
"Cuando el Camino prevalece, uno sirve;
when it does not, one withdraws into obscurity."
Cuando esto no sucede, uno se retira a la oscuridad.
Luo Wensong,
Luo Wensong
you really disappoint me today!
¡Hoy me has decepcionado mucho!
That doesn't sound like you at all!
¡Eso no se parece en nada a ti!
What should I say?
¿Qué debería decir?
Unmoved by worldly gain
Indiferente a las ganancias mundanas
or personal loss.
o pérdida personal.
Unmoved by worldly gain...
Indiferente a las ganancias mundanas...
Well said.
Bien dicho.
Do me a favor.
Hazme un favor.
Keep this "Ink Chronicles"
Conserva estas "Crónicas de tinta"
safe for me.
Seguro para mí.
Eldest Young Master!
¡El joven amo mayor!
Eldest Young Master,
Joven Maestro mayor,
the officers are already at the gate!
¡Los oficiales ya están en la puerta!
We have to leave now!
¡Tenemos que irnos ya!
Where are we going?
¿Adónde vamos?
Just come with me.
Ven conmigo.
Go in and search!
¡Entra y busca!
Don't let anyone escape!
¡Que nadie escape!
-Yes, sir!
-¡Sí, señor!
Yes, sir!
¡Sí, señor!
This way, sir.
Por aquí, señor.
Hurry up! Hurry!
¡Date prisa! ¡Date prisa!
Luo Wensong...
Luo Wensong...
Where exactly are you taking me?
¿Adónde me llevas exactamente?
I'm now a fugitive wanted by the court.
Ahora soy un fugitivo buscado por la corte.
If they find you with me,
Si te encuentran conmigo,
you'll be caught up in this.
Te verás envuelto en esto.
You...
Tú...
Hide here.
Escóndete aquí.
You can only leave after the officers are gone.
Solo podrás marcharte cuando los agentes se hayan ido.
Luo Wensong!
¡Luo Wensong!
Luo Wensong,
Luo Wensong
you must go on living and live well.
Debes seguir viviendo y vivir bien.
Anyone there?
¿Hay alguien ahí?
No!
¡No!
Let's go
Vamos
and search inside!
¡Y busca dentro!
Did you check over there?
¿Revisaste allí?
No.
No.
Go check over there!
¡Ve a echar un vistazo allí!
Yes, sir!
¡Sí, señor!
Eldest Young Master Tian,
El joven maestro Tian, ​​el mayor de todos,
did you find anyone?
¿Encontraste a alguien?
I've searched this area.
He buscado en esta zona.
No one found.
No se encontró a nadie.
Boss,
Jefe,
I've searched outside,
He buscado afuera,
and no one has been found.
y no se ha encontrado a nadie.
We didn't find anyone inside the house either.
Tampoco encontramos a nadie dentro de la casa.
If we can't catch anyone,
Si no podemos atrapar a nadie,
we won't be able to answer to our superiors.
No podremos rendir cuentas a nuestros superiores.
Sir,
Señor,
I know another place.
Conozco otro lugar.
Luo Wensong will definitely go there.
Luo Wensong sin duda irá allí.
Sir, follow me.
Señor, sígame.
Everyone, hurry up the mountain!
¡Todos, suban rápido la montaña!
Don't let Luo Wensong escape!
¡No dejes escapar a Luo Wensong!
Yes, sir!
¡Sí, señor!
Sir,
Señor,
this is the place.
Este es el lugar.
Surround Jingxin Hall!
¡Rodeen el Salón Jingxin!
-Yes, sir!
-¡Sí, señor!
Brother!
¡Hermano!
Butler!
¡Mayordomo!
Luo Wensong!
¡Luo Wensong!
Luo...
Luo...
Young Master!
¡El señorito!
To Jingxin Hall!
¡Al Salón Jingxin!
Young Master.
El señorito.
The officers have surrounded us from all sides.
Los agentes nos han rodeado por todos lados.
We can't escape.
No podemos escapar.
Fugitive Luo Wensong,
Fugitivo Luo Wensong
you have nowhere left to run!
¡No te queda ningún sitio adonde huir!
Come out and surrender now!
¡Sal y ríndete ahora!
Sir,
Señor,
I have an idea.
Tengo una idea.
What idea?
¿Qué idea?
Set the place on fire
Prender fuego al lugar
and see if they come out.
y veamos si salen.
Break the door!
¡Rompe la puerta!
Luo Wensong!
¡Luo Wensong!
If you don't come out,
Si no sales,
I'll burn Jingxin Hall to the ground!
¡Reduciré a cenizas el Salón Jingxin!
Wait for me inside.
Espérame adentro.
I'll go talk to them.
Iré a hablar con ellos.
Wensong!
¡Wensong!
Even if the sky falls,
Aunque el cielo se caiga,
we will face it together as a family!
¡Lo afrontaremos juntos como familia!
Grab your weapons!
¡Agarra tus armas!
You are Luo Wensong?
¿Eres Luo Wensong?
I am.
Soy.
County Magistrate Zhao Shen has orders
El magistrado del condado, Zhao Shen, tiene órdenes
that all members of your family must be taken back for investigation.
que todos los miembros de su familia deben ser llevados de regreso para ser investigados.
May I see the arrest warrant?
¿Puedo ver la orden de arresto?
The warrant is on its way.
La orden judicial está en camino.
Why do you have so many questions?
¿Por qué tienes tantas preguntas?
Young Master,
El señorito,
we were still too late.
Llegamos demasiado tarde.
Why are there so many constables?
¿Por qué hay tantos agentes de policía?
Luo Wensong!
¡Luo Wensong!
Surrender at once.
Ríndete de inmediato.
Tian Benchang.
Tian Benchang.
My father was right.
Mi padre tenía razón.
We really raised a fine, loyal dog.
Realmente criamos un perro excelente y leal.
Luo Wensong, you...
Luo Wensong, tú...
Tian Benchang?
¿Tian Benchang?
Does he work for us?
¿Trabaja para nosotros?
Why is he with those officers?
¿Por qué está con esos oficiales?
Chief Constable,
Jefe de policía,
may I negotiate something with you?
¿Puedo negociar algo con usted?
My aunt married out years ago
Mi tía se casó hace años.
and is no longer part of the Luo family.
y ya no forma parte de la familia Luo.
Can you let her go?
¿Puedes dejarla ir?
I will go with you.
Iré contigo.
And if he refuses,
Y si se niega,
what will you do?
¿Qué vas a hacer?
If you don't let my aunt go,
Si no dejas ir a mi tía,
I'm afraid I cannot surrender willingly.
Me temo que no puedo rendirme voluntariamente.
Luo Wensong, you're resisting arrest!
¡Luo Wensong, te estás resistiendo al arresto!
If you don't surrender today,
Si no te rindes hoy,
the officers will raze this place to the ground
Los oficiales arrasarán este lugar .
and wipe out your entire family!
¡Y acabar con toda tu familia!
I dare you!
¡Te reto!
Tian Benchang,
Tian Benchang,
you treacherous dog!
¡Perro traicionero!
Ping'an!
¡Ping'an!
Take them down!
¡Acaben con ellos!
Brother!
¡Hermano!
Young Master!
¡El señorito!
Don't let him escape!
¡No dejes que escape!
Sir!
¡Señor!
He's running away!
¡Está huyendo!
Get him!
¡Atrápenlo!
Sir!
¡Señor!
Don't let him get away!
¡No dejes que se escape!
Luo Wensong!
¡Luo Wensong!
Come out!
¡Salga!
Torch it!
¡Quémalo!
My brother...
Mi hermano...
My brother and my aunt are still inside...
Mi hermano y mi tía todavía están adentro...
Young Master, you can't go.
Joven amo, no puede irse.
Otherwise, the Old Master would've died in vain.
De lo contrario, el Viejo Maestro habría muerto en vano.
You must live!
¡Debes vivir!
Young Master,
El señorito,
let's go.
vamos.
Young Master.
El señorito.
Let's go.
Vamos.
Yes.
Sí.
[Jingxin Hall]
[Salón Jingxin]
Torch it!
¡Quémalo!
Young Master.
El señorito.
Are you alright?
¿Estás bien?
Let's rest here for a while.
Descansemos aquí un rato.
Young Master,
El señorito,
have a bite first.
Primero, come un bocado.
What...
Qué...
What do you want?
¿Qué deseas?
Hand over all your valuables.
Entregue todos sus objetos de valor.
Get up.
Levantarse.
Get up!
¡Levantarse!
Boss!
¡Jefe!
Search carefully.
Busca con atención.
This looks good.
Esto tiene buena pinta.
Let me see.
Déjeme ver.
Give it to me.
Dámelo.
This...
Este...
This is worthless.
Esto no vale para nada.
It's just an inkstick.
Es solo una barra de tinta.
Give it to me!
¡Dámelo!
It's really worth nothing.
Realmente no vale nada.
It's just an inkstick!
¡Es solo una barra de tinta!
Young Master!
¡El señorito!
Jixiang!
¡Jixiang!
I'll kill you!
¡Te mataré!
I'll strangle you!
¡Te estrangularé!
Let's go. Let's go!
¡Vamos! ¡Vamos!
Hurry, hurry!
¡Rápido, rápido!
Hurry!
¡Apurarse!
[Wang Cuiqiao]
[Wang Cuiqiao]
You're awake.
Estás despierto.
Thank you, Madam,
Gracias, señora.
for saving my buddy and me.
por salvarnos a mi amigo y a mí.
This place is desolate and dangerous.
Este lugar es desolado y peligroso.
Once you've rested,
Una vez que hayas descansado,
go home as soon as possible.
Vuelve a casa lo antes posible.
Okay.
Bueno.
Understood, Madam.
Entendido, señora.
I'm not some madam.
No soy ninguna señora.
I'm just a merchant.
Solo soy un comerciante.
Our family was also in trade once.
Nuestra familia también se dedicó al comercio en el pasado.
Is that so?
¿Es eso así?
What about now?
¿Y ahora?
Now...
Ahora...
we were brought down by scheming men.
Fuimos derribados por hombres intrigantes.
Our home is gone.
Nuestro hogar ha desaparecido.
It's just the two of us left.
Solo quedamos nosotros dos.
Then...
Entonces...
where are you going now?
¿Adónde vas ahora?
We're heading southeast
Nos dirigimos hacia el sureste.
to seek refuge with General Yu Dayong.
buscar refugio con el general Yu Dayong.
General Yu Dayong?
¿General Yu Dayong?
He's already redeployed from the southeast to the north.
Ya se ha trasladado del sureste al norte.
Since we've crossed paths here,
Ya que nos hemos cruzado aquí,
it must be fate.
Debe ser el destino.
Well, then,
Bueno, entonces,
travel with me.
Viaja conmigo.
I'm also
Yo también soy
going to find General Yu.
Voy a buscar al general Yu.
Let's go.
Vamos.
Young Master,
El señorito,
should we go with her?
¿Deberíamos ir con ella?
At least it'll be safer
Al menos será más seguro.
if we follow her.
si la seguimos.
But we still need to stay alert and play it by ear.
Pero aún así debemos mantenernos alerta y actuar según se necesite.
Heroine,
Heroína,
wait for us!
¡Espéranos!
Let's go.
Vamos.
Let's go. Our luggage.
Vamos. Nuestro equipaje.
I'll carry it.
Yo lo llevaré.
Let's go.
Vamos.
[Yaji Hall]
[Heard Hall]
Wonderful!
¡Maravilloso!
Wonderful, wonderful!
¡Maravilloso, maravilloso!
Sir!
¡Señor!
Welcome, welcome.
Bienvenidos, bienvenidos.
Okay, okay.
Vale, vale.
Likewise, likewise!
Igualmente, igualmente!
Congratulations!
¡Felicidades!
Thank you, thank you!
¡Gracias, gracias!
Thank you.
Gracias.
Likewise, likewise.
Igualmente, igualmente.
Please come in, please!
¡Pase, por favor!
Zhen.
Zhen.
Zhen,
Zhen,
listen to me.
escúchame.
I have something to tell you.
Tengo algo que contarte.
Tian Benchang,
Tian Benchang,
I have nothing to say to you.
No tengo nada que decirte.
Can you just let me go?
¿Puedes dejarme ir?
Listen to me, Zhen.
Escúchame, Zhen.
Now, there is
Ahora bien, hay
nothing standing between us anymore.
Ya no hay nada que nos separe.
I know
Sé
you resent me
Me guardas rencor.
and hate me.
y odiadme.
Back then, I was weak.
En aquel entonces, yo era débil.
I was wrong.
Me equivoqué.
But things are different now.
Pero ahora las cosas son diferentes.
My family,
Mi familia,
I—
I-
everything has changed.
Todo ha cambiado.
I have everything now.
Ahora lo tengo todo.
So what?
¿Así que lo que?
We'll never have to worry about orders again,
Nunca más tendremos que preocuparnos por los pedidos.
and we'll never have to scrape by.
y nunca tendremos que pasar penurias económicas.
From now on,
De aquí en adelante,
I'll make it up to you.
Te lo compensaré.
I'll treat you as well as I possibly can.
Te trataré lo mejor que pueda.
I'll come with a grand wedding procession
Vendré con una gran procesión nupcial.
-and marry you properly. -Tian Benchang!
-y casarme contigo como es debido. -Tian Benchang!
You clearly saw me there that night.
Me viste claramente allí esa noche.
Yes, I saw you.
Sí, te vi.
If you had been caught,
Si te hubieran atrapado,
you would've been an accomplice.
Habrías sido cómplice.
I was protecting you, Zhen.
Te estaba protegiendo, Zhen.
What about Luo Wensong?
¿Y qué hay de Luo Wensong?
Did he have to die?
¿Tenía que morir?
Luo Wensong was a fugitive wanted by the court.
Luo Wensong era un fugitivo buscado por la corte.
That was what he paid for resisting arrest.
Eso fue lo que pagó por resistirse al arresto.
Besides, Zhen,
Además, Zhen,
it was Luo Wensong who tore us apart.
Fue Luo Wensong quien nos separó.
He made my family suffer the deepest humiliation.
Hizo que mi familia sufriera la más profunda humillación.
Why are you speaking up for such a person?
¿Por qué defiendes a esa persona?
But what about the others in Jingxin Hall?
¿Pero qué pasa con los demás en el Salón Jingxin?
They were all cut from the same rotten cloth.
Todos estaban hechos del mismo material podrido.
That was entirely within the law!
¡Eso estaba totalmente dentro de la ley!
Besides,
Además,
that was all done by the officials.
Todo eso lo hicieron los funcionarios.
What has any of that to do with me?
¿Qué tiene todo eso que ver conmigo?
I saw it all!
¡Lo vi todo!
You set that fire.
Tú provocaste ese incendio.
I was in Jingxin Hall that day.
Ese día estuve en el Salón Jingxin.
I saw everything.
Lo vi todo.
You could've chosen not to set that fire!
¡Podrías haber optado por no provocar ese incendio!
Before, in my eyes,
Antes, a mis ojos,
my Benchang was a little timid
Mi Benchang era un poco tímido.
but kind
pero amable
and gentle.
y suave.
But the person you are today
Pero la persona que eres hoy
terrifies me.
me aterra.
How could you have become like this?
¿Cómo pudiste llegar a ser así?
Or
O
is this who you really are?
¿Eres tú realmente?
No matter what serious crime they committed,
No importa qué delito grave hayan cometido,
they should've been handed over to the authorities—
Deberían haber sido entregados a las autoridades.
not judged by you.
No juzgado por ti.
Yet, for your own selfish gain,
Sin embargo, para tu propio beneficio egoísta,
you killed them all!
¡Los mataste a todos!
How are you any different
¿En qué te diferencias?
from a bloodthirsty monster?
¿De un monstruo sediento de sangre?
Tian Benchang,
Tian Benchang,
we should never see each other again.
No deberíamos volver a vernos jamás.
I don't want to see you anymore.
No quiero volver a verte.
I did nothing wrong!
¡No hice nada malo!
Was I supposed to spend my whole life carrying the status of a servant,
¿Se suponía que debía pasar toda mi vida con la condición de sirviente?
letting others trample all over me?
¿Dejar que otros me pisoteen?
Let go of me!
¡Suéltame!
What's wrong with climbing my way up?
¿Qué tiene de malo ir escalando hasta llegar a la cima?
We grew up together—
Crecimos juntos—
you should understand me better than anyone!
¡Deberías entenderme mejor que nadie!
Zhen,
Zhen,
give me another chance.
Dame otra oportunidad.
Let's go back to how things were.
Volvamos a como eran las cosas antes.
Let's start over, okay, Zhen?
Empecemos de nuevo, ¿de acuerdo, Zhen?
You've truly lost your mind!
¡Realmente has perdido la cabeza!
The Li and Luo families
Las familias Li y Luo
stood side by side in the ink industry
se mantuvieron codo con codo en la industria de la tinta.
for decades.
Durante décadas.
I, too, competed in ink-making against Luo Hanzhang
Yo también competí en la fabricación de tinta contra Luo Hanzhang.
several times.
varias veces.
His talent for ink-making
Su talento para la fabricación de tinta
was no less than mine.
No era menos que la mía.
What a pity.
Qué lástima.
Today, the Luo family has fallen,
Hoy, la familia Luo ha caído,
and he died in the Capital, far from home.
Y murió en la capital, lejos de su hogar.
Grandfather...
Abuelo...
Actually...
De hecho...
Actually, the day the Luo family met with disaster,
En realidad, el día en que la familia Luo se encontró con el desastre,
I was at the Luo residence.
Me encontraba en la residencia Luo.
Did anyone see you?
¿Alguien te vio?
N-No.
N-No.
I went very discreetly,
Fui muy discretamente,
and no one noticed me.
y nadie me vio.
I went there that day
Fui allí ese día.
to ask for a betrothal annulment letter for Ronghua.
solicitar una carta de anulación de compromiso matrimonial para Ronghua.
But I never expected
Pero nunca lo esperé
that I would happen to witness
que yo presenciaría
Eldest Young Master Luo dying in the fire.
El joven maestro Luo, el mayor de los hermanos, muere en el incendio.
Zhen, oh, Zhen.
Zhen, oh, Zhen.
You must never
Nunca debes
mention this to anyone else again.
No vuelvas a mencionar esto a nadie más.
Grandfather,
Abuelo,
I just never expected
Nunca lo esperé
that Eldest Young Master Luo
ese joven maestro mayor Luo
would truly die like that.
Realmente moriría así.
When all is said and done,
Cuando todo está dicho y hecho,
he helped me once.
Me ayudó una vez.
I even have him to thank
Incluso tengo que agradecerle a él.
for my decision to pursue ink-making.
por mi decisión de dedicarme a la fabricación de tintas.
What do you mean?
¿Qué quieres decir?
Some time ago,
Hace un tiempo,
when I went to the Luo household to appraise pine soot,
Cuando fui a la casa de los Luo para evaluar el hollín de pino,
he said a few words
dijo unas pocas palabras
that awakened me.
Eso me despertó.
It made me realize that...
Me hizo darme cuenta de que...
deep down, I truly love making ink,
En el fondo, realmente me encanta hacer tinta,
and I want to pursue it.
y quiero seguir adelante con ello.
But that night,
Pero esa noche,
when I watched him die in the flames,
Cuando lo vi morir en las llamas,
I finally understood
Finalmente lo entendí
that there are truly people in this world
que realmente hay gente en este mundo
who treat ink-making
quienes tratan la fabricación de tinta
as the calling of their entire life—
como la vocación de toda su vida—
rising and falling with it,
subiendo y bajando con él,
living and dying with it.
vivir y morir con ello.
While I admired him deeply,
Si bien lo admiraba profundamente,
I was also frightened.
Yo también tenía miedo.
Suddenly, I no longer understood why I made ink.
De repente, dejé de entender por qué hacía tinta.
Was it out of momentary pride?
¿Fue por orgullo momentáneo?
For money?
¿Por dinero?
For love of it?
¿Por amor al arte?
Or for something else entirely?
¿O para algo completamente distinto?
I suddenly no longer knew.
De repente, ya no lo sabía.
It must have weighed heavily on you,
Debe haberte pesado mucho.
carrying such thoughts alone.
Soportar esos pensamientos en soledad.
Grandfather,
Abuelo,
I used to think
Yo solía pensar
Eldest Young Master Luo was just a madman,
El joven maestro mayor Luo era simplemente un loco.
caring about nothing but making ink,
No les importa nada más que hacer tinta,
and that we weren't on the same path.
y que no estábamos en el mismo camino.
But what he said
Pero lo que dijo
made a lot of sense to me.
Me pareció muy lógico.
An ink maker
Un fabricante de tinta
should be wholly focused and undisturbed.
Debe estar totalmente concentrado y sin interrupciones.
Focused and undisturbed.
Concentrado y sin interrupciones.
The path of ink-making
El camino de la elaboración de tinta
is full of hardships and obstacles.
Está lleno de dificultades y obstáculos.
We grind the ink, and the ink
Molemos la tinta y la tinta
shapes us in return.
y a su vez, nos moldea.
I've taught you how to make ink,
Te he enseñado cómo hacer tinta,
not so you could become some ordinary ink-maker
No para que te conviertas en un fabricante de tinta cualquiera.
scrambling to earn a living.
luchando por ganarse la vida.
What I want to pass on to you...
Lo que quiero transmitirte...
is the Way of Ink.
is the Way of Ink.
The Way of Ink?
The Way of Ink?
To remain upright and pure
To remain upright and pure
is the Li family's Way.
is the Li family's Way.
To live and die alongside the ink
To live and die alongside the ink
was Luo Wensong's Way.
was Luo Wensong's Way.
Forging ties with the powerful and noble
Forging ties with the powerful and noble
was Luo Hanzhang's Way.
was Luo Hanzhang's Way.
I truly hope
I truly hope
that one day
that one day
you can find your own Way.
you can find your own Way.
My own Way...
My own Way...
I hope
I hope
you can press forward
you can press forward
carrying those questions.
carrying those questions.
Keep questioning yourself,
Keep questioning yourself,
then shatter
then shatter
those doubts,
those doubts,
and temper yourself anew.
and temper yourself anew.
By repeating this process again and again,
By repeating this process again and again,
something indestructible
something indestructible
will surely take root in your heart.
will surely take root in your heart.
Grandfather,
Grandfather,
although I still don't know
although I still don't know
what my own Way is right now,
what my own Way is right now,
from now on,
from now on,
I'll do my best to trim every lamp wick carefully,
I'll do my best to trim every lamp wick carefully,
burn every bowl of lampblack well,
burn every bowl of lampblack well,
and make every block of ink as good as it can be.
and make every block of ink as good as it can be.
[Three Years Later]
[Three Years Later]
Father.
Father.
How is it going?
How is it going?
She's at the most critical stage?
She's at the most critical stage?
This is good stuff.
This is good stuff.
When I was out grocery shopping today,
When I was out grocery shopping today,
I met a traveling merchant.
I met a traveling merchant.
He said this is top-quality donkey-hide gelatin.
He said this is top-quality donkey-hide gelatin.
I thought
I thought
I'd make Zhen
I'd make Zhen
some chicken broth with it
some chicken broth with it
to replenish her strength.
to replenish her strength.
Grandfather!
Grandfather!
Zhen.
Zhen.
Look at your face—
Look at your face—
you look like a dirty little monkey.
you look like a dirty little monkey.
Grandfather.
Grandfather.
Come on, Grandfather.
Come on, Grandfather.
Come see! I've made it!
Come see! I've made it!
Let's go.
Vamos.
Mother.
Mother.
Come and see.
Come and see.
This one has large particles mixed in.
This one has large particles mixed in.
This one is a bit underdone.
This one is a bit underdone.
Father,
Father,
how is it?
how is it?
Zhen,
Zhen,
tell me,
tell me,
what is the key here?
what is the key here?
Lampblack with uneven color,
Lampblack with uneven color,
a coarse texture,
a coarse texture,
and a dull, dry appearance
and a dull, dry appearance
is considered mid- to low-grade.
is considered mid- to low-grade.
But if the color is pure black,
But if the color is pure black,
the texture fine,
the texture fine,
and it carries a subtle sheen,
and it carries a subtle sheen,
then it is of fine grade.
then it is of fine grade.
However, if the tung oil used is of exceptional quality,
However, if the tung oil used is of exceptional quality,
the burning method is proper,
the burning method is proper,
and the heat is precisely controlled,
and the heat is precisely controlled,
the lampblack produced will carry a subtle grey undertone within the black—
the lampblack produced will carry a subtle grey undertone within the black—
delicate and light.
delicate and light.
Then that's the rarest kind of all—
Then that's the rarest kind of all—
supreme-grade lampblack.
supreme-grade lampblack.
Good!
Good!
To know
To know
what it is and why it is so—
what it is and why it is so—
that's what makes
that's what makes
a qualified ink-maker.
a qualified ink-maker.
Father,
Father,
you mean...
you mean...
Zhen produced supreme-grade lampblack?
Zhen produced supreme-grade lampblack?
That's great, Zhen.
That's great, Zhen.
Grandfather.
Grandfather.
Does that mean
Does that mean
I've graduated from your tutelage?
I've graduated from your tutelage?
It's getting late.
It's getting late.
Add a meat dish
Add a meat dish
to tonight's dinner.
to tonight's dinner.
Alright, Father!
Alright, Father!
I'll go prepare it right away!
I'll go prepare it right away!
That's great!
That's great!
You're amazing, Zhen.
You're amazing, Zhen.
Honored ancestors,
Honored ancestors,
Zhen
Zhen
has studied the art of ink-making for three years.
has studied the art of ink-making for three years.
To keep her from growing proud and impatient,
To keep her from growing proud and impatient,
I would scold and criticize her
I would scold and criticize her
whenever she made progress,
whenever she made progress,
which caused her much suffering.
which caused her much suffering.
Yet this child
Yet this child
proved resilient,
proved resilient,
unafraid of obstacles,
unafraid of obstacles,
and progressed rapidly—
and progressed rapidly—
often putting even me to shame.
often putting even me to shame.
To me,
To me,
ink has always been life itself.
ink has always been life itself.
And yet
And yet
I was forced to give up halfway.
I was forced to give up halfway.
My heart had long since withered.
My heart had long since withered.
Thanks to heaven's grace,
Thanks to heaven's grace,
Zhen
Zhen
has attained proficiency in ink-making.
has attained proficiency in ink-making.
In just three years,
En tan solo tres años,
she's already produced supreme-grade lampblack.
Ella ya ha producido negro de humo de calidad suprema.
Ancestors above,
Antepasados ​​arriba,
Li Ink's legacy
El legado de Li Ink
has a worthy successor.
Tiene un digno sucesor.
We have a worthy successor.
Tenemos un digno sucesor.
I heard there was another dispute
Oí que había otra disputa.
at the ink workshop.
en el taller de tinta.
It's all because
Todo es porque
the master craftsmen are all talk and no skill.
Los maestros artesanos solo hablan y no tienen ninguna habilidad.
They can't produce good ink,
No pueden producir buena tinta,
yet all day long they keep demanding
Sin embargo, durante todo el día siguen exigiendo
higher wages.
salarios más altos.
Aunt Rujun,
Tía Rujun,
you've seen the ledgers yourself.
Usted mismo ha visto los libros de contabilidad.
Although our family's 10 years of heavy taxation have ended,
Aunque los 10 años de fuertes impuestos para nuestra familia han terminado,
business at the workshop is now bleak.
La situación del taller es ahora desalentadora.
Where would we get the spare money for them?
¿De dónde sacaríamos el dinero extra para comprarlos?
We
Nosotros
also want to
también quiero
pay them more.
Págales más.
It's just
Es solo
that times have changed.
que los tiempos han cambiado.
We truly can't afford it.
Realmente no podemos permitírnoslo.
Let alone the workers' wages,
Por no hablar de los salarios de los trabajadores,
even the monthly allowances for our own family members are still overdue.
Incluso las asignaciones mensuales para nuestros propios familiares siguen atrasadas.
[Li Zhengyou, Legitimate Grandson of the Seventh Branch—Son of Sun Wanyi]
[Li Zhengyou, nieto legítimo de la Séptima Rama—Hijo de Sun Wanyi]
I can only patch one hole by tearing open another.
Solo puedo tapar un agujero abriendo otro.
Jiangyue,
Jiangyue,
the ink workshop has its difficulties.
El taller de tinta tiene sus dificultades.
I understand.
Entiendo.
I vaguely heard a few days ago
Lo escuché vagamente hace unos días.
that those big clients who have patronized
que esos grandes clientes que han sido clientes
our business for years
nuestro negocio durante años
have now switched to the Tian family.
Ahora se han pasado a la familia Tian.
The Tian family?
¿La familia Tian?
They only got where they are
Ellos solo llegaron a donde están.
by seizing the Luo family's estate and workshops.
mediante la confiscación de la finca y los talleres de la familia Luo .
Without that,
Sin eso,
would their own abilities
sus propias habilidades
have been enough?
¿Ha sido suficiente?
Jingdong,
jingdong
watch your words.
Cuida tus palabras.
Aunt Rujun,
Tía Rujun,
we're all family here.
Aquí todos somos una familia.
What's there that cannot be said?
¿Qué hay que no se pueda decir?
The Tian family's rise was paved
El ascenso de la familia Tian fue allanado
with the Luo family's blood!
¡Con la sangre de la familia Luo!
Every coin they've earned is ill-gotten.
Cada moneda que han ganado es mal habida.
And now,
Y ahora,
they've even colluded
Incluso han conspirado.
with the County Magistrate
con el magistrado del condado
and powerful figures.
y figuras poderosas.
They don't even respect the Literary Association anymore.
Ya ni siquiera respetan a la Asociación Literaria.
In today's Huizhou,
En el Huizhou de hoy,
I'm afraid no one
Me temo que nadie
dares to s-stand against them.
se atreve a plantarles cara.
Zhengshen?
¿Zhengshen?
Seventh Grandmother.
Séptima abuela.
Grandfather.
Abuelo.
Father.
Padre.
Mother.
Madre.
Eldest Aunt.
Tía mayor.
Fourth Aunt.
Cuarta tía.
Don't you know
¿No lo sabes?
there's a family banquet
Hay un banquete familiar.
on the first and fifteenth of every month?
¿El primer y el quince de cada mes?
Why did you only show up after the meal was over?
¿Por qué llegaste solo después de que terminó la comida?
Don't just stand there!
¡No te quedes ahí parado!
Apologize to your seventh grandmother now.
Pídele disculpas a tu séptima abuela ahora.
Please forgive me, Seventh Grandmother.
Por favor, perdóname, Séptima Abuela.
[Li Zhengshen, Eldest Grandson of the Li Family’s Sixth Branch]
[Li Zhengshen, nieto mayor de la sexta rama de la familia Li]
Although I arrived late,
Aunque llegué tarde,
I've brought back
Lo he traído de vuelta
this divine elixir
este elixir divino
for you,
para ti,
Grandfather, and Father.
Abuelo y padre.
They say it's very effective.
Dicen que es muy eficaz.
Prolonging life
Prolongar la vida
and curing illnesses are just the basics.
y curar enfermedades son solo lo básico.
Even my father's leg—
Incluso la pierna de mi padre...
if he takes this elixir,
si toma este elixir,
given time,
Con el tiempo,
he'll be able to walk as swiftly as the wind.
Podrá caminar tan rápido como el viento.
You...
Tú...
Walk as swiftly as the wind, huh?
Camina tan rápido como el viento, ¿eh?
Father!
¡Padre!
Seventh Grandmother,
Séptima abuela,
I'm not fooling you.
No te estoy engañando.
This elixir is truly rare.
Este elixir es verdaderamente raro.
I heard that whenever Master Tian goes to the capital
He oído que cada vez que el Maestro Tian va a la capital
to curry favor with officials and nobles,
para ganarse el favor de funcionarios y nobles,
this elixir is included among the gifts he presents!
¡Este elixir está incluido entre los regalos que él presenta!
Unfilial son!
¡Hijo impío!
I'll beat you to death today!
¡Hoy te voy a matar a golpes!
Jingdong!
¡Jing Dong!
Let's talk about it when we get back.
Hablemos de ello cuando regresemos.
Zhengshen,
Zheng Shen,
do you still remember our family's rules?
¿Todavía recuerdas las reglas de nuestra familia?
On every festive reunion day,
En cada día festivo de reunión,
it is time to test the art of ink.
Es hora de poner a prueba el arte de la tinta.
Bring the inksticks up.
Traigan las barras de tinta.
This is...
Esto es...
This inkstick
Esta barra de tinta
smells wonderfully fragrant.
Tiene un aroma maravillosamente fragante.
And the pattern is
Y el patrón es
quite flashy and ornate.
bastante llamativo y ornamentado.
It must be Tian Ink's product.
Debe ser un producto de Tian Ink.
This one smells quite nice too.
Este también huele bastante bien.
Maybe it's
Tal vez sea
Chen Ink's product.
Producto de Chen Ink.
This piece looks
Esta pieza parece
very ordinary,
muy común,
with nothing ingenious about it.
No tiene nada de ingenioso.
Even the scent is quite common.
Incluso el olor es bastante común.
I'm afraid this one was made by my father.
Me temo que este lo hizo mi padre.
Then let's see
Entonces veamos
if Zhengshen got them right.
si Zhengshen las entendió bien.
[Zhao Ink]
[Zhao Ink]
[Cao Ink]
[Tinta Cao]
[Li Ink]
[Li Ink]
Look, Seventh Grandmother.
Mira, Séptima Abuela.
Ordinary, huh?
¿Normal, eh?
I'll beat you to death, you rebellious son!
¡Te voy a matar a golpes, hijo rebelde!
Calm down! Calm down.
¡Cálmate! ¡Cálmate!
Father,
Padre,
at least I recognized the inkstick you made!
¡Al menos reconocí la barra de tinta que hiciste!
I think you're
Creo que eres
far too consumed by your obsession!
¡Demasiado consumido por tu obsesión!
That's why you can't produce truly good ink.
Por eso no se puede producir una tinta realmente buena.
As the saying goes,
Como dice el dicho,
"Desire nothing,
"No desees nada,
and all things follow."
y todo lo demás sigue."
You've completely disgraced the Sixth Branch!
¡Has deshonrado por completo a la Sexta División!
Enough!
¡Suficiente!
What kind of behavior is this
¿Qué clase de comportamiento es este?
in front of your elders?
¿Delante de tus mayores?
Sorry, I lost my composure.
Lo siento, perdí la compostura.
I am indeed disappointed by my son's failure.
Estoy realmente decepcionado por el fracaso de mi hijo.
But I...
Pero yo...
But I hate myself even more.
Pero me odio aún más.
Ever since our family fell into hardship,
Desde que nuestra familia cayó en la pobreza,
our branch has shouldered the entire burden.
Nuestra sucursal ha asumido toda la responsabilidad.
Day after day, I exhaust every thought,
Día tras día, agoto cada pensamiento,
not daring to slacken for even a moment.
Sin atreverse a bajar la guardia ni por un instante.
I've spent my days and nights in the ink workshop.
He pasado mis días y noches en el taller de tinta.
I constantly fear my own abilities are insufficient
Temo constantemente que mis propias capacidades sean insuficientes.
to uphold the family name.
para honrar el apellido familiar.
I know I don't have much talent.
Sé que no tengo mucho talento.
But does that mean I should just give in?
Pero, ¿eso significa que debo rendirme?
Should I just be like you?
¿Debería ser como tú?
Jingdong,
jingdong
all these years,
todos estos años,
I've seen clearly how much effort and devotion
He visto claramente cuánto esfuerzo y dedicación
you've poured into Li Ink.
has vertido en Li Ink.
I have held it all in my heart.
Lo he guardado todo en mi corazón.
It has been hard on you.
Ha sido duro para ti.
Take a rest first.
Descansa primero.
Okay.
Bueno.
Have some water.
Toma un poco de agua.
Qiu'e,
Qiue,
Zhengliang!
¡Zhengliang!
Zhen?
¿Zhen?
Zhen!
¡Zhen!
Qiu'e, are you tired?
Qiu'e, ¿estás cansada?
Just seeing you makes all my tiredness disappear.
Con solo verte , todo mi cansancio desaparece.
Zhen,
Zhen,
what are you going to buy on Sibao Street?
¿Qué vas a comprar en la calle Sibao?
Did you bring enough money?
¿Trajiste suficiente dinero?
Here.
Aquí.
No, Qiu'e.
No, Qiue.
I don't need your money.
No necesito tu dinero.
On the contrary,
De lo contrario,
today
hoy
I came here to earn money.
Vine aquí para ganar dinero.
"Earn money?"
"¿Ganar dinero?"
How?
¿Cómo?
I want to take on lamp-burning work to make lampblack.
Quiero dedicarme a quemar lámparas para producir negro de humo.
Lamp-burning?
¿Lámparas encendidas?
What's that?
¿Qué es eso?
Producing lampblack takes time and effort,
Producir negro de humo requiere tiempo y esfuerzo,
so major ink workshops usually hire people to make it for them.
Por eso, los principales talleres de tinta suelen contratar a personas para que se encarguen de ello.
As long as you pay the deposit
Siempre y cuando pagues el depósito.
or have a guarantor,
o tener un avalista,
anyone can collect the raw materials
Cualquiera puede recolectar las materias primas.
and lamps to burn at home.
y lámparas para encender en casa.
And the major ink workshops
Y los principales talleres de tinta
will pay you
te pagaré
according to the quality produced.
según la calidad producida.
But if the quality is poor
Pero si la calidad es mala
and their reputation suffers,
y su reputación se ve perjudicada,
not only must you pay double in compensation,
no solo debe pagar el doble en compensación,
but in the worst cases,
pero en los peores casos,
you may be barred from entering the ink trade ever again.
Es posible que se le prohíba volver a entrar en el negocio de la tinta.
That...
Eso...
That won't do.
Eso no servirá.
Zhen,
Zhen,
I'll take care of all the household expenses.
Yo me haré cargo de todos los gastos del hogar.
You don't need to take such a risk.
No es necesario correr ese riesgo.
Zhengliang,
Zhengliang,
over the past few years,
en los últimos años,
my study of ink-making
mi estudio de la fabricación de tinta
has cost the family a great deal of money,
le ha costado mucho dinero a la familia,
with no return.
Sin retorno.
Now that I've succeeded in learning,
Ahora que he logrado aprender,
I naturally want to help earn some money for the household.
Naturalmente, quiero ayudar a ganar algo de dinero para la casa.
Besides...
Además...
Besides what?
¿Además de qué?
Besides,
Además,
the best sister-in-law in the world has just joined our family.
La mejor cuñada del mundo acaba de unirse a nuestra familia.
How can we mistreat her?
¿Cómo podemos maltratarla?
You're just like your brother,
Eres igual que tu hermano,
never serious.
Nunca es serio.
Fine then.
De acuerdo entonces.
Which ink workshop
¿Qué taller de tinta?
are you planning to go to?
¿Estás pensando ir?
Zhengliang,
Zhengliang,
I've thought it through.
Lo he pensado bien.
I want to go to Li's Ink Workshop.
Quiero ir al taller de tinta de Li.
Why go to the main family's workshop?
¿Por qué ir al taller de la familia principal?
One of their lampblack-making masters
Uno de sus maestros en la fabricación de negro de humo
left a few days ago,
se fue hace unos días,
so the quality of their lampblack has declined.
Por lo tanto, la calidad de su negro de humo ha disminuido.
So they'll be offering
Así que ofrecerán
a slightly higher price for lampblack.
un precio ligeramente más alto para el negro de humo.
Business is business.
Los negocios son los negocios.
Zhengliang,
Zhengliang,
let her do as she wishes.
Déjala hacer lo que quiera.
I believe
Yo creo
she's thought everything through carefully.
Ella lo ha pensado todo detenidamente.
When family members take on
Cuando los miembros de la familia asumen
lampblack work, they don't need to pay a deposit.
Los trabajadores que se dedican al hollín no necesitan pagar un depósito.
That works in our favor.
Eso nos beneficia.
Even so,
Aún así,
precisely because of that,
Precisamente por eso,
I insist on paying the deposit.
Insisto en pagar el depósito.
Otherwise, they'll think
De lo contrario, pensarán
we're taking advantage of them.
Nos estamos aprovechando de ellos.
That's right.
Así es.
Business is business—
Los negocios son los negocios-
you do the work, you get paid.
Si trabajas, te pagan.
If a deposit is due, pay it.
Si se debe pagar un depósito, páguelo.
Here, take this.
Toma esto.
No, Sister-in-law!
¡No, cuñada!
Take it!
¡Tómalo!
I really don't want it!
¡Realmente no lo quiero!
I'll figure something out myself.
Ya encontraré una solución por mi cuenta.
You two siblings—
Ustedes dos hermanos—
when you get stubborn,
cuando te pones terco,
you're exactly alike.
Sois exactamente iguales.
Listen to me,
Escúchame,
-take it! -No!
¡Tómalo! ¡No!
Zhen, don't refuse!
¡Zhen, no te niegues!
Just keep it.
Quédatelo.
Brother, Sister-in-law,
Hermano, cuñada,
don't worry.
no te preocupes.
I'll definitely earn money this time.
Esta vez seguro que gano dinero.
Okay.
Bueno.
We believe in you.
Creemos en ti.
Qiu'e,
Qiue,
when will you be done for the day?
¿Cuándo terminarás por hoy?
In a little while, I suppose.
Dentro de poco, supongo.
But this building is so grand.
Pero este edificio es grandioso.
Yihousheng?
¿Yihousheng?
[Yihousheng]
[Yihousheng]